正在高速接近，长官
Coming up on it fast, sir.
你能确定传感器的读数吗？
Are you certain of your sensor readings?
确定为某种飞船
Definitely a space vessel of some type.
- 来源？ - 未知
- Origin? - Unknown.
不可能是地球飞船
It could hardly be an Earth ship. There have been no flights
- 这一地区已多年没有航线 - 拦截到信号，长官
- into this sector for years. - I'm picking up a signal, sir.
舰长，是老式摩尔斯码信号
Captain, that's the old Morse code call signal.
- 谢谢，上尉 - C-Q，C-Q
- Thank you, lieutenant. - C-Q. C-Q.
我们听到了，上尉
We're reading it, lieutenant.
我记得你说这不可能是地球飞船
I thought you said it couldn't possibly be an Earth vessel.
不明白你为什么总喜欢看我出错
Fail to understand why it always gives you pleasure to see me proven wrong.
地球人情感上的弱点
An emotional Earth weakness of mine.
找到了
There it is.
是和DY-500型相似的老式地球飞船
An old Earth vessel similar to the DY-500 class.
比那更老，是DY-100型
Much older. DY-100 class, to be exact.
舰长
Captain...
最后建造的这种飞船也远在20世纪90年代
...the last such vessel was built centuries ago, back in the 1990s.
那飞船是被遗弃了，自动发射的信号
Then it's a derelict, its signal left on automatic.
或这艘老式地球飞船被外星人控制了
Or an old Earth ship being used by aliens.
- 武装状态 - 导流护盾开到最大
- Weapons status. - Deflector shields on maximum.
- 相位炮手就位，长官 - 汇报生物扫描结果
- Phasers manned, sir. - Bio-scanners report.
生命扫描仪获得心跳信息
Life science bio-scanners are picking up heartbeats from over there.
但不可能是人类，心跳太微弱
Can't be human, though. They're too faint and average,
平均每分钟四次
only four beats per minute.
传感器显示某种设备在这艘飞船上运作
Sensor reading, captain. Some sort of equipment functioning on that vessel.
所有甲板，全面戒备
All decks, go to full alert.
宇宙，最后的边疆
Space, the final frontier.
这是星舰进取号的航程
These are the voyages of the starship Enterprise.
它的五年任务，是去探索未知的新世界
Its five-year mission: to explore strange new worlds,
找寻新的生命与新的文明
to seek out new life and new civilizations,
勇踏前人未至之境
to boldly go where no man has gone before.
【星际迷航：原初】
TLF荣誉出品
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业途径
-=TLF字幕组=-
翻译：锁锁美同学
校对：喜马拉雅 Micezhang
第一季第二十二集
太空种子
舰长日志，星历3141.9
Captain's log, stardate 3141.9.
自拦截到陌生船只，已经过了一个小时
A full hour has elapsed since interception of the strange vessel.
我们的出现仍完全被无视
Our presence alongside is still being completely ignored.
虽然传感器显示船上仍然有设备运作
Although our sensors continue to show signs of equipment
和生命迹象，但对我们已不构成威胁
and life aboard, there's been no indication of danger to us.
武装部，保持战斗状态
Weapons Department, maintain battle stations.
其他部门，提高警觉
All other decks, stand by alert.
所有部门都收到命令，长官
All decks acknowledging, sir.
还在收到心跳信号
Continuing to pick up some form of heart action over there.
很微弱，很慢，依我推测
Very faint, very slow. Seems to be coming from about 60 or 70 bodies,
- 似乎来自六七十个个体 - 是外星人吗？
- as near as I can make out. - Alien bodies, Bones?
可能是，没有呼吸或其他类似迹象
Could be. There's no sign of breathing or any other form of respiration.
船体表面布满了流星坑
Hull surface is pitted with meteor scars.
但扫描仪显示出“星舰-植物湾”
However, scanners make out a name, SS Botany Bay.
可以查看注册表
Then you can check the registry.
注册表上没有这种型号的船只
No such vessel listed.
那一时期的记录只剩下片段了
Records of that period are fragmentary, however.
90年代中期正好是你们最后一次「世界大战」
The mid-1990s was the era of your last so-called "World War."
优生之战
The Eugenics Wars.
你们想通过优生优选来进化人种
Of course. Your attempt to improve the race through selective breeding.
打断一下，这不是我们的想法，史波克
Now, wait a minute, not our attempt, Mr. Spock,
是一群雄心勃勃的科学家
a group of ambitious scientists.
你了解的类型
I'm sure you know the type:
信仰理性，毫无感情
Devoted to logic, completely unemotional--
- 医生，请你… - 好了，先生们，别闹了
- Doctor, I would be pleased-- - All right, gentlemen, as you were.
牵引光束，锁定该飞船
Rig for tractor beam, helm. Lock onto that vessel.
- 发射牵引光束，长官 - 接管舰桥，史波克
- Rigging for tractor beam, sir. - Bridge is yours, Mr. Spock.
要加入登陆小队吗，医生？
Care to join the landing party, doctor?
要是你真想让我选…
Well, if you're actually giving me a choice--
我才没有
I'm not.
我需要一个熟悉20世纪地球的人
Oh, I'll need somebody familiar with the late 20th-century Earth.
该是历史学家大显身手的时候了
Here's a chance for that historian to do something for a change.
她叫什么？卖歌文？
What's her name? McGivers?
麦戈文上尉
Lieutenant McGivers.
请注意，以下人员请去传送室
Attention. The following personnel report to Transporter Room:
轮机长史考特，麦戈文上尉
Engineering Officer Scott, Lieutenant McGivers.
完毕
Acknowledge.
麦戈文收到，马上到
McGivers, on my way.
这艘船就像在等我们
It looks like that ship is expecting us.
热量读数在上升，空气中含有氧气
We read heat coming on, complete oxygen atmosphere.
有趣，准备好没，老骨头？
Very interesting. You ready, Bones?
不，我被分配在船上行医
No. Signed aboard this ship to practise medicine,
而不是让我的分子被传来传去
not to have my atoms scattered back and forth across space by this gadget.
你真守旧，麦考伊
You're an old-fashioned boy, McCoy.
历史学家在哪儿？
Where's that historian?
- 好，过来吧，麦… - 麦戈文，长官
- Well, come on, Lieutenant... - McGivers, sir.
启动
Energize.
史考特？
Scotty?
典型的地球式船舱，长官
Definitely Earth-type mechanisms, sir.
二十世纪的飞船
Twentieth-century vessel.
老式核能
Old-type atomic power.
庞大、笨重
Bulky, solid.
我想这就是所谓的“晶体管单元”
I think they used to call them "transistor units."
我很想拆开研究
I'd love to tear this baby apart.
上尉，这是睡眠舱
Captain, it's a sleeper ship.
假死状态？
Suspended animation?
我曾见过这样的老照片
I've seen old photographs of this.
直到大约2018年
Necessary because of the time involved
太空旅行都要进入这种假死
in space travel until about the year 2018.
从一个星球到另一个星球会花费数年
It took years just to travel from one planet to another.
经过几个世纪的旅行…
Is it possible they're still alive...
…他们可能还活着？
...after centuries of travel?
理论上可能
Theoretically possible.
不过我从没听过这种例子
I've never heard of it being tested for this long a period.
他们真俊俏
What a handsome group of people.
吉姆，有新的数据
Jim, I have a new reading.
这些灯肯定触发了什么装置
Lights must have triggered some mechanism.
舰长，看这儿
Captain, look here.
史考特
Scotty?
告诉我发生了什么？
Beats me what's happening.
我们触发了某些装置
We've triggered something, all right.
心跳加速，现在每分钟八次
Heartbeat's increasing, now passing eight beats per minute.
发现开始呼吸的迹象
And there are some signs of respiration beginning.
这个人可能最先醒来
This one was probably programmed to be triggered first.
他是首领吗？
Could he be the leader?
首领，上尉
The leader. Lieutenant.
是的，长官，首领会第一个复苏
Yes, sir. The leader was often set to revive first.
这样他就可以判断
This would allow him to decide
当下环境是否适合其他人复苏
whether the conditions warranted revival of the others.
现在心跳接近每分钟四十次
Heartbeat now approaching 40 per minute.
呼吸节奏稳步上升
The respiration pattern is firming up.
我认为是来自印度北部地区
From the northern India area, I'd guess,
可能是锡克人，他们是迷人的战士
probably a Sikh. They're the most fantastic warriors.
- 心跳现在达到五十二，还在持续上升 - 其他人呢？
- Heartbeat now 52 and increasing. - The others?
其他人没有变化，他们来自各个地区
There's no change. And they're all mixed types:
西方，欧洲中部，拉丁还有东方
Western, mid-European, Latin, Oriental.
来自二十世纪的人类即将苏醒
A man from the 20th century coming alive.
不一定，心跳速率下降
Maybe. Heartbeat dropping.
电路短路
Circuit shorting.
可能是灰尘引起的，心率三十，在快速下降
Probably some dust. Heartbeat now 30, dropping fast.
心房颤动，他快死了
There's a heart flutter. He's dying.
- 做点什么，舰长 - 可以吗？
- Do something, captain. - Can we?
花上一小时才能知道
Take an hour to figure out.
让他从里面出来会怎么样？
What happens if we get him out of there?
不这样做他马上会死
He'll die in seconds if we don't.
多久？
How long?
你们…
How long...
…睡了多久？
...have you been sleeping?
两个世纪，我们估计
Two centuries, we estimate.
登陆小队呼叫总部，连接
Landing party to Enterprise. Come in.
登陆小队继续，已经连接
Go ahead, boarding party, we read you.
锁定麦考伊医生
Lock in on Dr. McCoy's beam.
一名遇难者随他一起传回
He's transporting back with a casualty we discovered here.
真是壮观
Magnificent.
舰长日志，补充
Captain's log, supplemental.
在植物湾号旁已经停留十小时
Alongside the SS Botany Bay for ten hours now.
包括工程师和医生的侦查小队
A boarding party of engineering and medical specialists
已经完成对神秘船只的侦查
are now completing their examination of the mysterious vessel.
待这个遇难者急救完毕后
Attempts to revive other sleepers
我们将试图唤醒其他休眠者
await our success or failure with the casualty already beamed over.
麦考伊医生对他的强健体魄和恢复力深感惊奇
Dr. McCoy is frankly amazed at his physical and recuperative power.
- 登陆小组，这里是寇克 - 这里是史考特
- Kirk to boarding party. - Scott here.
史考特，有记录吗？日志什么之类的？
Scotty, any records? Log books of any kind?
没有，貌似在飞船起飞时
Negative, captain. It appears they were in suspended animation
- 他们是在假死状态 - 多少存活？
- when the ship took off. - How many alive?
十二个睡眠舱已损坏，还剩七十二个在运作
Twelve units have malfunctioned, leaving 72 still operating.
其中三十人是女人
Thirty of those are women.
寇克下线
Kirk out.
存活了七十二人
Seventy-two alive.
一群来自1990年代的人
A group of people dating back to the 1 990s.
重要的发现，史波克
A discovery of some importance, Mr. Spock.
那一年代还有许多谜团
There are a great many unanswered questions about those years.
你们历史上奇怪又暴力的年代
A strange, violent period in your history.
我没有发现有关植物湾号的任何信息
I find no record whatsoever of an SS Botany Bay.
舰长，DY-100号飞船
Captain, the DY-100 class vessel
只能用作行星间旅行
was designed for interplanetary travel only.
在那个时代，只有简单的核能
With simple nuclear-powered engines,
想要星际航行根本不可能
star travel was considered impractical at that time.
他们能成功前往下一个星系的概率
It was 10,000-1
是万分之一
against their making it to another star system.
而且，为什么没有旅行记录呢？
And why no record of the trip?
植物湾
Botany Bay...
是澳大利亚的海滨流放地，对吧？
...that was the name of a penal colony on the shores of Australia, wasn't it?
如果他们以此命名…
If they took that name for their vessel--
如果你想说这是艘流放船
If you're suggesting this was a penal deportation vessel,
那你的结论完全违背逻辑
you've arrived at a totally illogical conclusion.
你的地球在暗黑年代的边缘
Your Earth was on the verge of a Dark Ages.
许多人都被炸死了
Whole populations were being bombed out of existence.
比起浪费飞船让罪犯们遨游太空
A group of criminals could have been dealt with
还有更有效的处理方法
far more efficiently than wasting one of their most advanced spaceships.
对，我的推论就那么多
Yes. So much for my theory.
我还想听听你的理论
I'm still waiting to hear yours.
一个理论需要事实来支撑，舰长
Even a theory requires some facts, captain.
目前为止…
So far...
- 还没有证据 - 这点让你恼怒了，史波克
- ...I have none. - And that irritates you, Mr. Spock.
- 恼怒？ - 对
- Irritation? - Yeah.
我没有那种情绪
I am not capable of that emotion.
我的错，史波克
My apologies, Mr. Spock.
你怀疑有危险？
You suspect some danger in them?
不了解真相常常导致危险，舰长
Insufficient facts always invites danger, captain.
嗯，那我最好套出些事实来
Well, I'd better get some facts.
- 继续调查 - 是，长官
- Rig for towing. - Aye, aye, sir.
- 制定前往星际基地12的航线 - 是，长官
- Make course for Starbase 12. - Aye, sir.
可以了
That'll be all.
- 老骨头？ - 他没事
- Bones? - He'll live.
- 干得不错 - 不，我医术没好到那种程度
- My compliments. - No, I'm good, but not that good.
他体内有东西拒绝死亡
There's something inside this man that refuses to accept death.
看这个，就算他病成这样
Now, look at that. Even as he is now,
他的心脏瓣膜也是你我的两倍强壮
his heart valve action is twice the power of yours or mine.
肺部效率是我们的1.5倍
Lung efficiency, 50 percent better.
优良人种
An improved breed of human.
这就是优生战争产生的原因
That's what the Eugenics War was all about.
我估计他可以一手举起我俩
I'd estimate he could lift us both with one arm.
要是他的智力赶上体力就有趣了
Be interesting to see if his brain matches his body.
医生，他会活下来吗？
Doctor, will he live?
看来会的，上尉
It appears he will, lieutenant.
我要和你谈谈
I'd like to talk to you.
如果要我评价你今天登陆时表现…
If I were to rate your performance as a member of the landing party today--
我知道，长官，对不起
I know, sir. I'm sorry.
上尉，请记住，每个船员的表现
Lieutenant, at any one time, the safety of this entire vessel might depend
都会影响飞船的安全
on the performance of a single crewman aboard.
还有你找到了
And the fact that you find a man
符合你个人喜好的男人…
strangely compelling to you personally--
不是个人喜好，舰长，是专业方向
Not personally, captain, professionally.
我专攻历史
My profession is historian,
现在发现了来自过去的活标本
and to find a specimen from the past, alive...
我是指，研究他的想法将会很有趣
I mean, the sheer delight of examining his mind.
同时他们也富有冒险精神
And men were more adventuresome then.
胆大，更多样
Bolder, more colourful.
- 没错，长官，的确如此 - 好的
- Yes, sir, I think they were. - Good.
恕我直言，此时更易忽略错误
If I can have honesty, it's easier to overlook mistakes.
- 就这么多 - 好的，长官
- That's all. - Yes, sir.
你做指挥官真是可惜了，吉姆
A pity you wasted your life on command, Jim.
你已经成为公正的心理学家
You'd have made a fair psychologist.
公正？
Fair?
医务室呼叫实验室
Sickbay to lab.
- 他们有什么异常吗？ - 一切正常，医生
- Anything new on those bios? - They all came out fine, doctor.
很好，麦考伊下线
Good. McCoy out.
掐死我还是割破喉咙，选一个
Well, either choke me or cut my throat. Make up your mind.
这是英语，我似乎在梦里听过
English. I thought I dreamed hearing it.
我在哪儿？
Where am l?
你在…
You're in--
你在床上用刀抵着你医生的喉咙
You're in bed holding a knife at your doctor's throat.
回答我的问题
Answer my question.
割断颈动脉会更有效
It would be most effective if you would cut the carotid artery,
就在左耳下方
just under the left ear.
我喜欢勇敢的人
I like a brave man.
我只是试图避免争吵
I was simply trying to avoid an argument.
你在联邦星舰进取号上，你的船拖在后面
You're aboard the United Spaceship Enterprise. Your vessel is in tow.
我记得有个声音，是不是说…
I remember a voice. Did I hear it say...
我睡了两个世纪？
...I had been sleeping for two centuries?
没错
That is correct.
你们的舰长在哪儿？我有许多问题
Where is your captain? I have many questions.
- 舰桥 - 我这儿有个病人
- Bridge. - I have a patient here
- 有很多问题要问，舰长 - 马上到
- with many questions, captain. - On my way.
詹姆士·寇克，这艘星舰的指挥官
James Kirk, commanding the starship Enterprise.
我知道
I see.
你的名字是？
And your name?
我先问几个问题
I have a few questions first.
你的飞船驶向哪里？
What is your heading?
驶向星际基地12，伽玛400星系中的行星…
Our heading is Starbase 12, a planet in the Gamma 400 star system...
它是这一区域的指挥基地
...our command base in this sector.
这样说可以吗？
Is that of any use to you?
我的属下…
And...
…怎么样了？
...my people?
七十二个生命维生舱仍在正常运行
Seventy-two of your life-support canisters are still functioning.
- 你会复苏他们 - 只有我们到了星际基地12
- You will revive them. - As soon as we reach Starbase 12.
我知道了
I see.
那么…
And now...
我的名字是可汗
Khan is my name.
- 可汗，姓呢？ - 就是可汗
- Khan. Nothing else? - Khan.
你们起飞的具体日期是什么？
What was the exact date of your liftoff?
我们知道是在1990年代初期，但…
We know it was some time in the early 1990s, but--
我有点累了，医生
I find myself growing fatigued, doctor.
下次再谈这个问题好吗？
May we continue this questioning at some other time?
我们需要事实，可汗先生，只要一点时间
The facts I need, Mr. Khan, will take very little time.
比如，你们远征的性质
For example, the nature of your expedition.
吉姆，等会再谈吧
Jim, a little later might be better.
舰长，在我恢复期间
Captain, I wonder if I could have something to read
可以看一些书吗？我曾是工程师
during my convalescence. I was once an engineer of sorts.
我对你们飞船的技术手册很感兴趣
I would be most interested in studying the technical manuals on your vessel.
好，我明白，你有两百年的知识要补
Yes, I understand. You have 200 years of catching up to do.
的确
Precisely.
任何一个病人都可以从显示屏获悉这些
They're available to any patient on the viewing screen.
麦考伊医生会告诉你如何使用图书馆
Dr. McCoy will show you how to tie into the library tapes.
谢谢，舰长，你很合作
Thank you, captain. You are very cooperative.
这个可汗和我想象的20世纪人不同
This Khan is not what I expected of a 20th-century man.
我注意到他在使用我们的技术库
I note he's making considerable use of our technical library.
这是常见的礼节，史波克
Common courtesy, Mr. Spock.
他将在我们的世纪度过余生
He's going to spend the rest of his days in our time.
这只是帮他补上知识
It's only decent to help him catch up.
他可不可能是…
Would you...
…优选种产物？
...estimate him to be a product of selected breeding?
有这个可能，舰长
There is that possibility, captain.
按年龄来说有可能
His age would be correct.
在1993年，一群这样的超人类
In 1993, a group of these young supermen
夺取了超过40个国家的主权
did seize power simultaneously in over 40 nations.
他们简直是超人
Well, they were hardly supermen.
他们激进傲慢，逐渐发生内战
They were aggressive, arrogant. They began to battle among themselves.
因为科学家们高估了一个事实
Because the scientists overlooked one fact:
超能力会孕育超级野心
Superior ability breeds superior ambition.
有趣，如果是真的
Interesting, if true.
他们制造了一群亚历山大，拿破仑
They created a group of Alexanders, Napoleons.
我收集了一些资料做了调查
I've collected some names and made some counts.
据调查，当超人类们被击溃时
By my estimate, there were some 80 or 90
仍有八九十个下落不明
of these young supermen unaccounted for when they were finally defeated.
事实不是历史书上那样的
That fact isn't in the history texts.
你难道会向那些厌战的人宣布
Would you reveal to war-weary populations
仍有八十个拿破仑存活？
that some 80 Napoleons might still be alive?
- 随船历史学家，上尉… - 玛拉·麦戈文
- Ship's historian. Lieutenant-- - Marla McGivers.
对
Yes.
据说你也参加了我的救援
I am told you participated in my rebirth.
只帮了小忙
In a small way.
我正在了解船身结构
I've been reading up on starships, but they have one luxury
但有件奢侈品手册里没提
not mentioned in the manuals.
那是什么？
I don't understand.
美丽的女人
A beautiful woman.
我叫可汗，请坐下陪我一起
My name is Khan. Please sit and entertain me.
我想了解你们飞船的历史
I'd like some historical information about your ship.
- 飞船的目的是… - 你怎么把发型
- Its purpose and-- - And why do you wear your hair
弄得这么糟？
in such an uncomplimentary fashion?
这样很舒服
It's comfortable.
但并不漂亮
But it's not attractive.
这里
There.
舒服
Soft.
自然
Natural.
- 简单 - 可汗先生，我是来办公事的
- Simple. - Mr. Khan, I'm here on business.
你不觉得这样很愉快吗？
You find no pleasure here?
我专于科学，人…
My interest is scientific. Men of--
以及过去的人
That is the world of the past.
你一定明白，事实上，和你们世纪的人谈话…
I'm sure you understand, actually to talk to a man of your century...
这里
There.
简单
Simple.
舒适
Soft.
愉快的记忆
Please remember.
也许改天你会更想谈过去的事
Perhaps some other time when you feel more like talking about the past.
很高兴你能来
I'm glad you came.
希望你再来
Please do it again.
真令人惊叹
Very impressive.
我们邀请了五星上将参加晚餐？
Are we expecting a fleet admiral for dinner?
上尉麦戈文建议以此欢迎可汗来到我们世纪
Lieutenant McGivers' idea to welcome Khan to our century.
她到底对他多着迷？
Just how strongly is she attracted to him?
嗯，并没有条款禁止浪漫，吉姆
Well, there aren't any regulations against romance, Jim.
我是指公事上，不是个人感情上，老骨头
My curiosity is official, not personal, Bones.
嗯，他有吸引力，几乎是电磁力
Well, he has a magnetism, almost electric. You felt it.
对麦戈文来说这比历史还要吸引人
And it could overpower McGivers with her preoccupation with the past.
谢谢
Thank you.
希望你能带我去参加晚餐
I hoped you might guide me to our dinner engagement.
很好
Very good.
- 画工很精细 - 这是名为弗拉维奥的角斗士
- Fine technique. - It's a gladiator named Flavius.
- 他曾经… - 你为我
- He once-- - And you've rearranged
重新打理了头发
your hair for me.
很好
Excellent.
都是历史中有血性的男人
All bold men from the past.
查理德、莱夫·埃里克松、拿破仑
Richard, Leif Ericson, Napoleon.
这样的男人，是你的兴趣？
A hobby of yours, such men?
我的荣幸
I am honoured.
谢谢
Thank you.
但是我警告你…
But I caution you...
…这种男人敢拿他想要的任何东西
...such men dare take what they want.
原谅我的好奇心，可汗先生
Forgive my curiosity, Mr. Khan,
但我的军官们想知道你的冒险经历
but my officers are anxious to know more about your extraordinary journey.
还有你如何从历史书中钻出来的
And how you managed to keep it out of the history books.
冒险，舰长，是冒险
Adventure, captain. Adventure.
地球上什么都不剩了
There was little else left on Earth.
那场战争结束了暴政
There was the war to end tyranny.
很多人认为这是高尚的行为
Many considered that a noble effort.
暴政，先生，团结人类的手段？
Tyranny, sir, or an attempt to unify humanity?
统一，先生？
Unify, sir?
就像鞭子下的动物吗？
Like a team of animals under one whip?
我知道这些年代的事
I know something of those years, remember.
一个宏伟梦想的年代，一个伟大抱负的年代
It was a time of great dreams, of great aspiration.
在一系列独裁下
Under dozens of petty dictatorships.
最终会有一人统治
One man would have ruled eventually,
就像罗马在凯撒的统治下，想想他的成就
as Rome under Caesar. Think of its accomplishments.
那么你的同情就…
Then your sympathies were with--
你是一名卓越的战略家，舰长
You are an excellent tactician, captain.
你让副指挥攻击…
You let your second-in-command attack...
自己则坐观敌人弱点
...while you sit and watch for weakness.
你似乎喜欢套用军事术语
You have a tendency to express ideas in military terms, Mr. Khan.
但这是社交场合
This is a social occasion.
据说社交场合暗藏战争
It has been said that social occasions are only warfare concealed.
很多人觉得社交更诚实
Many prefer it more honest,
更开放
more open.
你逃跑了，为什么，害怕了吗？
You fled. Why, were you afraid?
- 我从未害怕 - 但你留在这个时代
- I've never been afraid. - But you left at the very time
- 需要勇气 - 我们掌管世界秩序
- mankind needed courage. - We offered the world order!
我们？
We?
聪明，真聪明
Excellent. Excellent.
请原谅，先生们和女士们
But if you will excuse me, gentlemen and ladies.
我又一次疲乏了
I grow fatigued again.
舰长，请允许我回到我的住处
With your permission, captain, I will return to my quarters.
我向你道歉
I wanted to apologise.
他们无权那样对你
They had no right to treat you that way.
十分理解，因为对于这里来说，我是一团迷
Quite understandable, since I'm something of a mystery to them.
对我来说你不是谜，我很清楚你是谁
You're no mystery to me. I know exactly who you are.
是吗？
Do you?
莱夫·埃里克森，狮心王理查德，拿破仑
Leif Ericson, Richard the Lion-Hearted, Napoleon.
不知你是否喜欢我们时代的生活
I don't know if you're going to like living in our time.
那我不得不把它改造成我喜欢的
Then I'll have to remold it to my liking.
- 拜托别 - 走
- Please don't. - Go.
要不然就自愿留下
Or stay, but do it because it is what you wish to do.
如何？
Well?
我就再留一会儿
I'll stay a little longer.
你打算客气多久？
How many minutes do you graciously offer?
- 我是说… - 我对此厌倦了
- I only meant-- - This grows tiresome.
你现在得求我让你留下来
You must now ask to stay.
我愿意留下来
I'd like to stay.
求你了
Please?
打开你的心胸
Open your heart.
你会对我坦诚吗？
Will you open your heart?
会
Yes.
我想要拿下这艘飞船
I intend to take this ship.
- 你同意吗？ - 请别让我…
- Do you agree? - Please don't ask me to--
我需要你的帮助
I need your help.
你不会伤害其他人吧？
You won't harm anyone?
- 你在质问我？ - 没
- Now you question me? - No.
你会帮我吗？
Will you assist me?
- 拜托，可汗，别让我… - 那滚吧
- Please, Khan, don't ask-- - Leave me, then.
我说，滚
Go, I say.
不
No.
我保证
I promise.
一切顺从你的意思
I'll do anything you ask.
姓名：可汗，正如我们今天所知
Name: Khan, as we know him today.
姓名：可汗·努尼恩·辛格
Name: Khan Noonien Singh.
从1992年至1996年，从亚洲到中东
From 1992 through 1996, absolute ruler
是统治你们四分之一世界的独裁者
of more than a quarter of your world, from Asia through the Middle East.
最后被推翻的暴君
The last of the tyrants to be overthrown.
我必须承认，先生们
I must confess, gentlemen,
我一直暗地里敬佩这个人
I've always held a sneaking admiration for this one.
他是最优秀的暴君，也是最危险的
He was the best of the tyrants, and the most dangerous.
某种程度上，他们是超人类
They were supermen, in a sense.
强壮，勇敢，当然也野心勃勃
Stronger, braver, certainly more ambitious, more daring.
先生们，对这个独裁者不能抱有浪漫主义思想…
Gentlemen, this romanticism about a ruthless dictator is--
史波克，野蛮是人类固有的特征
Mr. Spock, we humans have a streak of barbarism in us.
尽管很可怕，但是事实
Appalling, but there, nevertheless.
他的统治下没有大屠杀
There were no massacres under his rule.
- 也没有自由 - 为了反击他才发动战争
- And as little freedom. - No wars until he was attacked.
先生们
Gentlemen.
史波克，你误解我们了
Mr. Spock, you misunderstand us.
我们可以同时敬仰他和反对他
We can be against him and admire him, all at the same time.
- 不合逻辑 - 没错
- Illogical. - Totally.
舰长呼叫
This is the captain.
对可汗房间实行24小时监控，马上执行
Put a 24-hour security on Mr. Khan's quarters, effective immediately.
抱歉，舰长，我…
I'm sorry, captain, I was...
…陷入沉思了
...lost in thought.
我的门
My door.
从外面反锁了，还有人守着
Locked from outside, a guard posted.
对可汗·努尼恩·辛格的特殊待遇
Unusual treatment for Khan Noonien Singh.
聪明
Excellent.
我想你是在电脑系统里找到的吧？
You identified me with your computer system, I imagine?
我现在就要你回答
I'd like those answers now.
首先…
First...
…你们星际旅行的目的
...the purpose of your star flight.
全新的生活，创造新世界的机会
A new life, a chance to build a world.
其他事情我想你也不明白
Other things I doubt you would understand.
为什么？
Why?
因为我不是控制遗传学的产物？
Because I'm not a product of controlled genetics?
舰长，虽然你的能力让我很感兴趣
Captain, although your abilities intrigue me...
你的精神和肉体上都更逊一筹
...you are quite honestly inferior. Mentally, physically.
实际上我很惊奇
In fact, I am surprised how little improvement
多年来人类改善不大
there has been in human evolution.
哦，技术有所进步…
Oh, there has been technical advancement...
…但人类本身进步太小
...but how little man himself has changed.
看来我们能在你们世纪做得更好，舰长
Yes, it appears we will do well in your century, captain.
还有其他问题吗？
Do you have any other questions?
谢谢
Thank you.
我已得到答案
They've all been answered.
让开
Move away.
奥托
Otto.
华金
Joaquin.
旅途结束了
The trip is over.
战争即将开始，只是这次，我们赢得的不是世界
The battle begins again. Only this time, it's not a world we'll win,
而是整个宇宙
it's a universe.
卡蒂
Kati.
- 航线正确，舰长，2级曲速 - 继续维持
- On course, sir. Warp factor 2. - Maintain.
- 舰桥 - 舰长，门卫倒下了
- Bridge. - Captain, security here.
可汗逃了
Khan's escaped.
- 打开安全警报 - 已开启，舰长
- Sound security alert. - Security alert, captain.
遭到通信干扰，舰长
Communication channels are jammed, captain.
涡轮升降机不起作用
Turbo elevators inoperative.
遭到干扰，舰长
Jammed, captain.
大气控制器被切断了
Atmospheric controls cut off.
没用了，他们在轮机室获得了更高权限
Useless. They're on override in Engineering.
轮机室
Engineering.
史考特，这里是舰桥
Scotty, this is the bridge.
舰长！
Captain!
- 发生什么事了？ - 他此时
- What's going on down there? - He's not able to answer you
无法回答你，舰长
at the moment, captain.
你的船现在归我，我已经关闭了
Your ship is mine. I have shut off the life-support system
舰桥的生命支持系统
to your bridge,
关闭了你们的逃生通道
jammed up your exit routes.
欢迎你们来洽谈
I am willing to negotiate.
所有船舱覆盖类神经气体
Flood all decks with neural gas.
无法实施，入侵者破坏了系统
Impossible. Intruder control systems inoperative.
可汗对我们的技术手册研究得很透彻
Mr. Khan was very thorough in his study of our tech manuals.
联系星际基地12
Contact Starbase 12.
所有通道都被阻断，舰长
All channels are totally jammed, captain.
聪明，每个应急措施都预料到了
Brilliant. Every contingency anticipated.
里面的空气现在肯定很稀薄了
Your air should be getting quite thin by now.
- 你们投降吗？ - 绝不
- Do you surrender the bridge? - Negative.
聪明点，舰长
Academic, captain.
拒绝，舰桥上每个人都会窒息而死
Refuse, and every person on the bridge will suffocate.
星历3142.8
Stardate 3142.8.
他们控制了我的船
They have my ship...
抛弃了他们自己无用的飞船
...discarding their own worthless vessel.
舰桥现在仅剩少量空气
Only moments of air left on the bridge now.
应该嘉奖乌乎拉上尉
Commendations recommended for Lieutenant Uhura,
一级技术师哈里森和托雷
Technicians First Class Thule and Harrison...
斯皮内利上尉
...Lieutenant Spinelli...
当然还有史波克
...and of course, Mr. Spock.
我要负全部责任
I take full responsibility.
我尽…
I take full...
除了人以外…
Nothing ever changes...
其他事物一点没变
...except man.
你们获取了技术进步
Your technical accomplishments?
改进机械装置，生产效率可以翻倍
Improve a mechanical device and you may double productivity.
但若改进人类…
But improve man...
你会获得一千倍，我就是这样的人
...and you gain a thousandfold. I am such a man.
跟我一起
Join me.
我不会亏待你
I'll treat you well.
我需要你操纵这艘复杂的船只
I need your training to operate a vessel this complex.
寇克舰长在哪儿？
Where is Captain Kirk?
看来我犯了个严重的错
I see now I made one serious error.
你是通信官
You are the communications officer.
启动屏幕
Engage the viewing screen, please.
不！
No!
我应该意识到，让你们在舰桥上一起窒息
I should have realised that suffocating together on the bridge
可以创建你们之间的英雄情结
would create heroic camaraderie among you.
但要坐着袖手旁观
But it is quite a different thing to sit by
则困难许多
and watch it happening to someone else.
请看屏幕
Engage the viewing screen.
你应该很清楚这个医疗减压室吧，医生
I'm sure you recognise your medical decompression chamber here, doctor.
也知道那气压计的意味
And the meaning of that indicator.
你们的舰长将要死去
Your captain will die.
如果你加入我们，史波克先生
If you join me, Mr. Spock...
我会留他一命
...I will save his life.
我的飞船没什么用
My vessel was useless.
我需要你们的飞船来选择一个
I need you and yours to select a colony planet,
会听从我们命令的殖民地星球
one with a population willing to be led by us.
被你征服
To be conquered by you.
有一艘星舰会使这更简单，不是吗？
A starship would make that most simple, wouldn't it?
你们每个人都会轮流进去
Each of you in turn will go in there.
其他人则看着他死去
Die while the others watch.
可汗，我没有理由在这里看着吧？
Khan, there's no reason I must watch this, is there?
我以为你很坚强
But I hoped you would be stronger.
若有一人能加入我们，任何一人…
If any one of you joins me, anyone...
…我就会让他活着
...I'll let him live.
反抗是无用的
It's so useless!
我们的通讯受阻
We've lost the channel.
我们怎样才能获得画面？
How do I regain picture?
没关系
It does not matter.
舰长已经死了
The captain is dead.
史波克是下一个
Take Mr. Spock next.
（减压室）
可汗说要密切关注他，他或许会同意合作
Khan said to watch him very closely. He may decide to cooperate.
舰长，我救了你，请别杀他
Captain, I saved your life. Now, please don't kill him.
看见你很吃惊，舰长，虽然也很欣慰
I'm surprised to see you, captain, though pleased.
我自己也有点欣慰
I'm a little pleased myself.
- 现在什么情况？ - 可汗在简报室挟持了我们的人
- Situation. - Khan is holding our staff
他的属下控制了飞船
in the Briefing Room. His men have control of the ship.
我们的唯一机会是入侵控制回路
Our only chance is the intruder control circuit,
他把舰桥的回路切断了
although he's cut it off at the bridge.
沿着走廊走会有个中继器
There's a relay junction down the corridor.
在其它所有甲板释放气体
Gas all decks but this one.
军械库，这里是可汗，报告情况
Armoury, this is Khan. Report.
罗德里格斯？
Rodriguez?
凌？
Ling?
麦弗逊？有谁在吗？报告情况！
McPherson? Anyone? Report status!
- 可汗在哪？ - 不知道
- Where's Khan? - I don't know.
在气体进来时他冲了出去…
He got out just as the gas...
- 这是寇克 - 除了轮机室，麻醉气体已释放完毕
- Kirk here. - Anesthesia gas in all sections
有人刚刚隔断了那里的信号
except Engineering. Someone just closed that line.
舰长，收到
Captain, acknowledge.
气体无法达到轮机室
Unable to flood Engineering section.
- 我怀疑… - 这里是史考特
- I suspect-- - This is Scott.
舰长正在前往轮机室
Captain's headed for the Engineering section.
- 我紧跟其后，以防… - 不行
- I'll follow in case-- - Negative.
趁麻醉持续，我们应该夺回船只
We must retake the vessel while the anesthesia lasts.
在军械库碰面，这里已清理干净，史波克下线
Meet me in the armoury. I'm blowing it clear first. Spock out.
如果我的理解正确
If I understood your manuals...
那你的飞船正在过载…
...that's an overload in progress.
几分钟后，它会像爆炸的太阳一样燃烧
Your ship flares up like an exploding sun within minutes.
我比你强壮五倍
I have five times your strength.
你打不赢我的
You're no match for me.
舰长日记，星历3143.3
Captain's log, stardate 3143.3.
飞船控制权已被夺回
Control of the Enterprise has been regained.
我希望下一个决定不再如此困难
I wish my next decisions were no more difficult.
把可汗和他的属下
Khan and his people,
流放到教改中心真是浪费人才
what a waste to put them in a reorientation centre.
麦戈文如何处置？
And what do I do about McGivers?
卡带已准备好了，舰长
Record tapes engaged and ready, captain.
听证会现在开始
This hearing is now in session.
根据星际舰队司令部赋予我的权力
Under the authority vested in me by Starfleet Command...
我声明所有指控和陈述
...I declare all charges and specifications
已经处理完毕
in this matter have been dropped.
吉姆，虽然同意你有权利…
Jim, agreed you have the authority--
史波克，我认为我们正在驶向鲸鱼座阿尔法星系附近
Mr. Spock, I believe our heading takes us near the Ceti Alpha star system.
没错，舰长，五号行星可供居住
Quite correct, captain. Planet number five there is habitable,
虽然有些荒芜
although a bit savage, somewhat inhospitable.
但不比澳大利亚的
But no more than Australia's
植物湾流放地差
Botany Bay colony was at the beginning.
那些人是去征服一片大陆的，可汗先生
Those men went on to tame a continent, Mr. Khan.
你能征服整个世界吗？
Can you tame a world?
你看过弥尔顿吗，舰长？
Have you ever read Milton, captain?
看过
Yes.
我懂了
I understand.
玛拉·麦戈文上尉
Lieutenant Marla McGivers.
在军事法庭审判和跟他们一起流放当中
Given a choice of court-martial
二选一
or accompanying them there...
流放很艰辛
It will be difficult.
历经千辛万苦，需要为生存而战、需要觅食
A struggle at first, even to stay alive, to find food.
我和他一起，长官
I'll go with him, sir.
坚强的女人
A superior woman.
我会带上她
I will take her.
我得到了其他我想要的东西
And I've gotten something else I wanted.
需要征服的世界，在建的帝国
A world to win, an empire to build.
听证会结束了
This hearing is closed.
虽然身为苏格兰人，但我却没读过弥尔顿
It's a shame for a good Scotsman to admit it, but I'm not up on Milton.
当堕天使路西法掉入深渊时曾说过
The statement Lucifer made when he fell into the pit:
“与其在天堂做奴隶，倒不如在地狱称王”
"It is better to rule in hell than serve in heaven."
一百年后再来看这个世界一定会很有趣，舰长
It would be interesting, captain, to return to that world in 100 years...
去看看你今天种的种子开出何种花果
...and learn what crop had sprung from the seed you planted today.
是的，史波克
Yes, Mr. Spock.
的确如此
It would indeed.
TLF字幕组欢迎你，欢迎有志之士加入
TLF中文字幕站http://tlfsubs.eastgame.org/